Mss.B.V462
American Philosophical Society
John Vaughan papers, 1768 - Circa 1936
Mss.B.V462
American Philosophical Society
5.0 Linear feet Ca. 850 items
The collection of about 850 items covers the period from 1782 to c. 1936, with the bulk dating to the 1780s to 1840s. The collection is divided into four series. Series I contains correspondence relating to a wide variety of topics, including French and English politics, business, trade, religious matters, and personal affairs. Many of the items are letters of introduction. There is also information on John Vaughan’s immigration to America, Joseph Priestley, vaccines and inoculation (with Jefferson's comments on the same), Vaughan's business in Philadelphia, and the American Philosophical Society. Also included in this series are 2 boxes with copies of Vaughan correspondence as well as miscellaneous notes by E. W. Madeira, gathered in the course of his research on Vaughan in the 1930s. Series II consists of three volumes. Included are two of Vaughan's commonplace books. One, entitled, "J. Vaughan's book," May 17, 1779 (47 pp., in Latin; 870/L34), includes mostly Latin notations. The other commonplace book, dated 1783 (ca. 66 pp.; B V 462.c), includes comments on several prominent Americans, such as Benjamin Rush and David Rittenhouse, as well as American society generally. The third volume is a copybook with thirty letters spanning the period 1784 to 1801 (B V462.1). Series III includes material relating to Vaughan's administration of the estate of the Philadelphia merchant Samuel Merrick, 1796-1822 (Vaughan-Merrick Papers, B V462.m; 2 boxes). Series IV consists of correspondence between Vaughan and the DuPont Co. for which he served as agent (B V462.4; photocopies of 73 letters).
Ca. 850 items.
Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
Box 1-8
Other Finding Aids note
Typed tables of contents (excepting items formerly in Misc. Mss.) are included in the boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection includes c. 500 letters to or from John Vaughan formerly in Miscellaneous Manuscripts (Misc. Ms.); c. 280 items from the Madeira-Vaughan Collection (Purchased from E. W. Madeira ($4000.00) and accessioned, 06/--/1946.); three letters purchased from Fleming; Aug. 22, 1962 (formerly B V462.2); one letter presented by Earl E. Moore; Feb. 1965 (formerly B V462.3); and one letter with Accession number 1981 45ms (formerly B V462.5). The copies of the 73 DuPont letters were acquired from Euletherian Mills Historical Society and accessioned 1970. See in-house shelf list for additional sources and accession numbers and dates.
Biographical/Historical note
John Vaughan (1756–1841, APS 1784) was a wine merchant, philanthropist, and long-time treasurer and librarian of the American Philosophical Society. A native of England, Vaughan moved to Philadelphia in 1782. He soon was one of the most respected members of Philadelphia society, largely because of his tireless support of numerous literary, scientific and benevolent causes. Over the course of his five decades of service to the American Philosophical Society, Vaughan met and corresponded with many eminent Americans and Europeans.
John Vaughan was born in London, England, in 1756. He was one of eleven children of Samuel Vaughan, a London merchant and West India planter, and Sarah Hallowell, daughter of Benjamin Hallowell, a Boston merchant and founder of Hallowell, Maine. Vaughan grew up in a liberal household. The family attended religious services by the dissenting minister and political radical Richard Price (1723-1791, APS 1785). His older brothers, Benjamin Vaughan (1751-1835, APS 1786), who became a prominent diplomat and political reformer, and William Vaughan, who eventually served as the promoter of the London docks, resided with the dissenter Joseph Priestley (1733-1804, APS 1785) during their studies at the Warrington Academy. John apparently attended Palgrave School, a popular school for boys founded by the poet and essayist Anna Letitia Barbauld (1743-1825) and her husband, the Reverend Rochemont Barbault.
In 1776, in preparation for a mercantile career, John Vaughan was sent abroad, first to Jamaica, where he spent one year, and then to France, where he arrived in 1778. While working for a merchant house in Bordeaux, Vaughan became acquainted with Benjamin Franklin and his grandson William Temple Franklin (1760-1823, APS 1786). After the conclusion of the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and France, Vaughan, who, as a British subject, was faced with possible arrest or deportation, declared himself an American. However, when he was unable to receive from the American minister a certificate to that effect, he removed to Spain. In 1782 Vaughan came to the United States. He settled in Philadelphia, where he became a prosperous wine merchant.
Vaughan almost immediately dedicated much of his energy and resources to the American Philosophical Society. He became a member in 1784, treasurer in 1791, and librarian in 1803, serving in these posts until his death in 1841. In his five decades of service under the presidencies of David Rittenhouse (1732-1796, APS 1768), Thomas Jefferson, Caspar Wistar (1761-1818, APS 1787), Robert M. Patterson (1787-1854, APS 1809), William Tilghman (1756-1827, APS 1805) and Peter Stephen Du Ponceau (1760-1844, APS 1791), Vaughan kept the society’s books and accounts, oversaw its publications, and carried on its extensive correspondence. He diligently worked to expand the society’s collections through requests for private donations, exchanges of material, and appeals to European and American learned societies to donate their publications. (Vaughan eventually bequeathed his own library of 600 volumes to the society.) In 1824 he compiled a catalog for the library which he hoped would one day become a National Library. He also acquired the catalogs of other libraries so that scholars working in the Philosophical Society would know what was available elsewhere. Vaughan contributed generously to the construction of Philosophical Hall, and in 1795 he made a subscription toward the proposed western expedition of the French botanist André Michaux (1749-1802).
John Vaughan was not a scholar or scientist himself. However, he encouraged and supported the work of scholars, especially those interested in Native American linguistics and ethnohistory, like his friend Du Ponceau. He obviously enjoyed the company and friendship of “learned men,” and he worked actively to introduce scholars to each other, either through his correspondence or personally. For example, he hosted Sunday breakfasts for visitors to Philadelphia, and he was a regular at the so-called Wistar Parties, that brought together companies of scholars for more formal gatherings. After 1822 Vaughan did not just work in Philosophical Hall; he also resided there. He had already been renting for several years the cellar for the storage of his wines and liquors. He now established his home in rooms formerly occupied by the studio and gallery of the painter Thomas Sully (1783-1872, APS 1835). In 1823, Sully painted the librarian’s portrait.
Vaughan was well-known to the citizens of Philadelphia. His reputation as a generous and “good” man was due not only to his work with the Philosophical Society, but also to his untiring commitment to be patron to all deserving young men. Indeed, Jared Sparks (1789-1866, APS 1837) described him as a “recommender-general of all schoolmasters, inventors, young men just entering on their professions, and every sort of personage, whose characters are good, and who can be benefited by his aid.” In 1838 a group of admirers founded the “Vaughan Club” to honor their friend. Members were required to bring a bottle of the finest and rarest wine to their annual meetings. The meeting could not be adjourned until every bottle had been consumed.
Vaughan was particularly admired for his philanthropic activities. “Who is there here who does not know Mr. John Vaughan?,” asked the Boston Daily Courier in the fall of 1841, when Vaughan was in his late eighties. “His doctrine is good works, and his practice squares with it.” He was an active member of the First Congregational Unitarian Church, where he occasionally occupied the pulpit. He also belonged to many local learned and philanthropic societies, and he served as officer in most. He was president of the Pennsylvania Institution for the Instruction of the Blind, president of the Society of Sons of St. George, a director of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, vice president of the Athenaeum of Philadelphia, a trustee of the Unitarian Society, and a councilor of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania and the Athenian Institute. Furthermore, he was secretary and treasurer of the Philadelphia Chamber of Commerce, a director of the Insurance Company of North America and of the Delaware Insurance Company; and an agent of the firm of E. I. Du Pont de Nemours and Company.
In 1841 Vaughan, who never married, died in his rooms in Philosophical Hall. The beneficiaries of his bequest included his friend Jacob Snider, Jr., who had been brought up by Vaughan, as well as various learned and philanthropic societies, including the APS. His funeral was attended by numerous respected citizens and representatives of the charitable and learned institutions he had supported during his life. A printed card that was circulated among those in attendance described John Vaughan simply as a man “Who went about doing good.”
Vaughan’s fifty years of service to the Philosophical Society were overshadowed by the discovery after his death that he had mingled the Society’s funds with his own. As a result, the Philosophical Society never published a biographical memoir of its long-term librarian and treasurer.
Related Archival Materials note
For a collection of papers related to the Vaughan Club, dated 1838-1841, see Misc.Ms. (1 folder). The correspondence between John Vaughan and his brother Benjamin is filed separately as part of the Benjamin Vaughan papers (B V46.p; 1 box). For several letters by members of the Vaughan family, including Sarah, Barbara, and Rebecca, see Vaughan Family papers (B V46.f). For a journal by John's father Samuel Vaughan, see B V464. A memorandum by John Vaughan, concerning the right of the society to answer a request, is written on the same sheet as letter from Joseph Sansom to Robert Patterson; Monday morning [1790?] (Misc.Ms.Collection). A very short biographical note by Vaughan concerning Richard Champion and his family is in Champion's Considerations on the present situation of Great Britain and the United States of America... 2nd ed. 1784 (382 C36 c.2).
Naval History Note
There is at least one item in the Vaughan Papers which may be of interest to naval historians:
Biddle, James. Letter to John Vaughan. 1826 May 11. Naval appointments. 3 pages.
Early American History Note
The John Vaughan Collection is a large collection that reflects the life of this prominent Philadelphian and active member of the American Philosophical Society. The collection is large, but not as large as the Benjamin Vaughan Collection, the collection of John’s brother’s papers. John lived in Philadelphia and his correspondence contains information on elite society in this city. It also contains data on the operations of the APS during his lifetime. The collection has been well described and inventoried in MOLE.
Adams, John, 1735-1826; American Philosophical Society.; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891; Bowditch, Nathaniel, 1773-1838; Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858; Cooper, Thomas, 1759-1839; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel, 1739-1817; Du Pont, Eleuthère Irénée, 1771-1834; Du Pont, Victor Marie, 1767-1827; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823; Furness, William Henry, 1802-1896; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909; Harrison, Richard; Hollinshead, Benjamin M; Ingenhousz, Jan, 1730-1799; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859; Jay, John, 1745- 1829; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Madeira family.; Madison, Dolley, 1768-1849; Martineau, Harriet, 1802-1876; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870; Monroe, James, 1758-1831; Norris, William, 1802-1867; Peters, Richard, 1743-1828; Priestley, Joseph, -- 1733-1804. -- Unitarianism explained and defended.; Repplier, Agnes, 1855-1950; Sampson (Ship).; Snider, Jacob; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866; Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, -- prince de Bénévent, -- 1754-1838.; Taney, Roger Brooke, 1777-1864; Vaughan, Benjamin, 1751-1835; Vaughan, Samuel; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Waterhouse, Benjamin, 1754-1846; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; Williams, Jonathan.; Diaries.; Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Institutional Records; Medicine.; Natural History; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Commerce.; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Social life and customs.; Philadelphia History; Planetariums.; Political Correspondence; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Verses.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1768-1922; c. 850 items.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  This series includes c. 500 letters to or from John Vaughan formerly in Miscellaneous Manuscripts (Misc. Ms.); c. 280 letters from the Madeira-Vaughan Collection; three letters purchased from Fleming; Aug. 22, 1962 (formerly B V462.2); one letter presented by Earl E. Moore; Feb. 1965 (formerly B V462.3); and one letter with accession number 1981 45 ms (formerly B V462.5). There are also 2 boxes of Miscellaneous notes gathered by Edward W. Madeira during the course of his research on John Vaughan in the 1930s.
  Arrangement note
  The letters are arranged chronologically. The "Miscellaneous notes by E. W. Madeira" are boxed separately.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of c. 850 letters as well as miscellaneous notes and papers. It covers the period from 1782 to 1922, with the bulk dating to the 1780s to 1840s. The series also includes miscellaneous letters of members of the Madeira family to or from many prominent individuals, dated between 1890 and 1922. Most of the few essays and notes in this collection were not authored by Vaughan but instead seem to have been copied from other sources. This includes, for example, “Rules for a New Settlement in Cuba” (October 1809). Also included in this series are two boxes (“Miscellaneous notes, etc. by E. W. Madeira”) with material related to Madeira’s research on John Vaughan. They include copies of Vaughan letters, research notes, inventories of Vaughan letters in Madeira’s possession, biographical essays, as well as correspondence with various individuals, including librarians and editors, contacted by Madeira in the course of his research. Madeira assembled this material in the 1930s.
  Vaughan was a well-connected individual who corresponded widely and actively with many individuals in the United States and abroad. Among the writers and recipients of letters in this series are George Washington, John Jay, Aaron Burr, Joseph Priestley, Edward Everett Hale, Thomas Jefferson, John Adams, John Quincy Adams, Washington Irving, Harriet Martineau, Richard Peters, Jr., Agnes Repplier, Roger B. Taney, Edmond Genet, Jared Sparks, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, and Daniel Webster. There are also numerous letters from family members, especially his brother William. That John Vaughan enjoyed a reputation as a charitable man is reflected in the many letters of introduction, requests for assistance, and notes of appreciation for gifts that he received throughout his more than four decades as secretary, librarian, and treasurer of the APS.
  The topics covered in the letters are as varied as the correspondents; they range from politics to science, from mutual acquaintances to religious matters, from philanthropic concerns to business affairs. One topic is, for example, vaccination. There is a subscription list for a publication on vaccination (27 April 1803), a letter by Vaughan to Jefferson that accompanied several copies of the publication (28 April 1803), and a letter by Benjamin Waterhouse in which he discusses the difficulty of promoting vaccination among the residents of Boston. Waterhouse reports that his effort to inoculate have been met “with the blackest ingratitude from those very persons for whose benefit I labor the most” (9 May 1803).
  A few of the letters from John Vaughan to Thomas Jefferson (some of which are photocopies) deal with matters pertaining to the American Philosophical Society. There is, for example, a letter that requests the President of the United States to affix his signature to membership certificates of the APS (8 May 1804). In another letter Vaughan informs Jefferson that Mr. Peale, Dr. Collin, Dr. Fothergill, and “the famous Dr. Humboldt” and his two companions will be taking copies of the Transactions with them on their planned trip to Washington (29 May 1804).
  Several of Jefferson's letters deal with matters pertaining to the University of Virginia, including one in which he discusses the progress in its construction (8 March 1820). Another letter refers to the seal that Dr. Cooper had made for the university by the engraver Robert Lovett (9 April 1820). Jefferson subsequently explained the meaning of the elements incorporated in the seal, including a Minerva (24 April 1820). That the university was initially not in a position to hire “special professors” is evident from a letter in which Jefferson explains the limited annuity and large debt with which the institution was burdened in its early days (8 April 1821).
  Many of the letters in the collection from Jefferson to Vaughan deal with publications and other objects Jefferson hoped to procure with Vaughan’s assistance. Most interesting in this regard is a letter in which Jefferson lays out his plans to restock his personal library which he had donated to Congress after the “destruction of the Capitol and library at Washington” (1 March 1815). Jefferson also secured the assistance of Stephen Girard and several individuals in France to help with the purchase of books (11, 15 and 30 July 1815). Jefferson regularly asked Vaughan to acquire books for him. In 1817, for example, Jefferson wrote to Vaughan that “the season for my annual call for books and wines from France” was now recurring (7 June 1817, also 8 April 1818). Many of the letters include financial information about Jefferson’s orders, including the funds he planned to spend on books and wine. Jefferson’s last letter in the collection alludes to his financial difficulties that were due to his “unskillful stewardship,” as he explained. It introduces his grandson, Thomas Jefferson Randolph, who was charged with selling part of his grandfather’s property (24 March 1826). Vaughan occasionally turned to Jefferson for assistance, as he did when he asked for help in securing employment in the Navy for Caspar Wistar’s son (10 November 1822).
  That Jefferson was not the only one who relied on Vaughan’s help is illustrated by many items in this series. Noteworthy in this regard are the letters from Louisa Catherine and John Quincy Adams. The couple asked Vaughan to procure two indentured servants for them, including “a Woman not to be under twenty and the Boy about fourteen.” Mrs. Adams subsequently thanked Vaughan for the “German Woman and Boy” he was “so obliging to purchase” for her (October and November 1817).
  A particularly interesting letter by John Adams describes Joseph Priestley as “Certainly one of the greatest Men in the World, and certainly one of the weakest” (23 November 1813). John Vaughan and his brother Benjamin were instrumental in bringing their friend and mentor Priestley to the United States. Several letters in this series, including some by Joseph Priestley, Jr., testify to their friendship.
  A number of letters reflect Vaughan’s commitment to philanthropic interests and activities, including a school for the blind. Lydia H. Sigourney offered several stanzas in recognition of “that noble institution for the Blind, which owes so much to [Vaughan’s] benevolent interest” (4 October 1838), and the letter by Richard Henry Lee applauds Vaughan for the accomplishments of the school of which Vaughan was considered a founder (undated). There are also letters that refer to the efforts of Jabob Snider, Jr., on behalf of the blind, including his plan to print a bible for their use (Preston to Snider, [20?] May 1834; Friedlander to Willig, 8 October 1834).
  A particularly interesting item Among the letters related to Vaughan’s involvement with the Unitarian Church is one by James Taylor, in which Taylor informs Vaughan of his failed attempt to get the pastor, Dr. Furness, to give advance notice whenever he planned to preach on slavery or abolition (20 May 1841).
  The collection includes a number of letters to or from Jacob Snider, Jr., who was brought up by Vaughan and worked in his counting house (Will, 6 May 1837). Some of this material dates to the period after Vaughan's death. This includes references to Snider’s successful rescue of “that poor deluded girl [Elizabeth Legg ] from the clutches of … a villain,” a matter that is discussed in several letters, including the ones by I. Shields, W. Sharp, and her sister Jane Legg (September 1844). A number of additional items from and to Jacob Snider, Jr., also shed light on the legacy of the Vaughan brothers. For example, Snider made a number of documents in the Vaughan bequest available to various people. The letters by Jared Sparks refer to Sparks’s use of documents from the Benjamin Vaughan estate (February and March 1851), and Washington Irving used an “orderly book of the American Army at Valley Forge” (30 January 1850).
  A document that sheds some light on the nature of the Vaughan Club, a social club that was founded by several of John Vaughan’s friends in Philadelphia, is the “Club Song” that was prepared by the “Committee of one” in 1839. A related item consists of verses written in honor of Vaughan’s 85th birthday at the request of Snider. Vaughan was unable to take part in the celebration; “his place was supplied with his portrait which was adorned with an appropriate wreath” (15 January 1841). There is also an inventory and other documents relating to John Vaughan’s estate (1841; 2 February 1842; 7 January 1843), and will (6 May 1837). Vaughan’s friend Jared Sparks subsequently expressed the hope that a “worthy person” would write a memoir of the well-liked Philadelphia merchant and philanthropist (17 February 1851).
  - Letter to Marquis de Modêne, Feb. 15, 1768; 6 1/4" x 7 3/4"; Voltaire, 1694-1778
    Chateau de Feney, L.S. 1p. and add. In French. MADEIRA-VAUGHAN COLLECTION
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Jan. 1, 1780; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Passy, Copy of L. On same sheet with copy of letter from B. Franklin to R. Morris; Jan. 19, 1782. In re Mr. Vaughan's going to America. FILM54-58 FRAME 116 MADEIRA-VAUGHAN COLLECTION
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Jan. 14, 1781; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Passy, Copy of L. On same sheet with copy of letter from B. Franklin to R. Morris; Jan. 19, 1782. In re Mr. Vaughan's intention of settling in America. FILM54-58 FRAME 116 MADEIRA-VAUGHAN COLLECTION
  - Letter to Mr. [Richard ?] Harrison, Nov. 6, 1781; 7 1/4" x 9"; Jay, John, 1745-1829
    Madrid, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Introduces Mr. John Vaughan. MADEIRA-VAUGHAN COLLECTION
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Jan. 1, 1782; Vaughan, Samuel, 1720-1802
    London, Copy of L. On same sheet with copy of letter from B. Franklin to R. Morris; Jan. 19, 1782. Recommends his embarking for Philadelphia MADEIRA-VAUGHAN COLLECTION
  - Certification in re John Vaughan, Jan. 5, 1782; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804